Estelle Ishigo papers, 1941-1957
UCLA Library Special Collections
Estelle Ishigo papers
1941-1957
2010
Ishigo, Estelle
5 boxes (2.5 linear ft.) 6 oversize boxes
Estelle (Peck) Ishigo (1899- ) was born in Oakland, California. She attended Otis Art Institute where she met and married San Franciscan Nisei, Arthur Ishigo (ca. 1929). Following Pearl Harbor, both were fired from their jobs and Arthur was ordered to a concentration camp. Estelle voluntarily accompanied him, and they were eventually assigned to Heart Mountain concentration camp in Wyoming. Estelle documented life at the camp through her artwork. The collection consists of documents, records, correspondence, photographs, paintings, pencil drawings and sketches, and watercolor sketches related to Estelle Ishigo's life in the Pomona Assembly Center, California and the Heart Mountain Relocation Center, Wyoming. There is also material related to the Ishigo's postwar resettlement in Southern California.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Original online finding aid from 1997
Register of the Japanese American Research Project (JARP): The Estelle Ishigo Papers, 1941 - 1957
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4233210
Biography
Estelle (Peck) Ishigo was born in Oakland, California, 1899; attended Otis Art Institute; met and married San Franciscan Nisei, Arthur Ishigo (ca. 1929); following Pearl Harbor, both were fired from their jobs and Arthur ordered to a concentration camp; Estelle voluntarily accompanied him and they were eventually assigned to Heart Mountain concentration camp in Wyoming; Estelle documented life at the camp through her artwork; they lived in poverty for many years following the war; Arthur died, 1957; fellow Heart Mountain inmates helped Ishigo republish her 1972 book, Lone Heart Mountain, ca. 1984; filmmaker Steven Okazaki made a documentary of Ishigo's life titled, Days of Waiting; she died before seeing the film (1990).
Additional Biographical Narrative
Estelle Ishigo was a Caucasian artist and daughter of a concert singer and portrait and landscape artist. Born in Oakland, California, Estelle was surrounded by music and art. At age four, she showed promising abilities in painting and singing. By age twelve, she learned to play the violin.
While attending Otis Art School in Los Angeles, Estelle met Arthur Shigeharu Ishigo (1902-1957), a San Francisco-born Nisei and aspiring actor. They were married in 1928.
At the outbreak of World War II, husband and wife were placed in the Pomona Assembly Center. Eventually, Estelle accompanied her husband to the Heart Mountain Relocation Camp in Wyoming where she was commissioned by the War Relocation Authority (WRA) to sketch her experiences.
During her three and a half year internment, Estelle helped with the camp newspapers and played violin in the camp's Mandolin Band. When the war ended and the camps closed, the Ishigos left Heart Mountain and returned to Southern California where they lived in a trailer camp and worked in fish canneries in San Pedro. Two years later, Arthur procured work at the Los Angeles International Airport which enabled them to visit New York, Chicago, Dallas, and Mexico City.
After Arthur passed away in 1957, Estelle stayed in seclusion until the California Historical Society asked to show her paintings in their Months of Waiting exhibit.
Discovered by the Hollywood Chapter of the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL), Estelle's Lone Heart Mountain was published in 1972, a book which she wrote and sketched during her encampment years.
Just two years before Estelle's death, Producer/Director Steven Okazaki released the film Days of Waiting about Estelle's life as one of the few Caucasians to be interned with 100,000 Japanese Americans. The film earned the Academy Award for Best Documentary Short Subject and received the prestigious George Peabody Award. Estelle Ishigo's extraordinary artistic talent as well as her devotion to her husband make Days of Waiting a poignant retrospection.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of documents, records, correspondence, photographs, paintings, pencil drawings and sketches, and watercolor sketches related to Estelle Ishigo's life in the Pomona Assembly Center, California and the Heart Mountain Relocation Center, Wyoming. The collection also includes material related to the Ishigo's postwar resettlement in Southern California. Additionally there are short essays, manuscripts, and draft manuscripts by Estelle Ishigo.
Expanded Scope and Content Note
The Estelle Ishigo papers are a part of the Japanese American Research Project (JARP) Collection (Collection 2010). JARP is considered one of the finest collections of primary sources in the United States on Japanese immigration history. Conducted under the sponsorship of the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL), JARP was a socio-historical research project which began in 1962 and lasted until 1972. During the course of the project, the JARP staff amassed a sizable body of material in the Japanese language which became the core of the JARP Collection. Additions were made as they were obtained.
The Ishigo papers is part of the Nisei personal papers section of JARP's manuscript holdings. It consists mainly of documents, records, correspondence and other materials relating both to Estelle Ishigo's life in the Pomona Assembly Center, California, and the Heart Mountain Relocation Center, Wyoming, as well as documents, correspondence and materials relating to Arthur and Estelle Ishigo's postwar resettlement in Southern California. The papers also contain Estelle Ishigo's manuscripts, short essays and draft manuscripts. Noteworthy is the presence of Estelle's various paintings, sketches and watercolors.
For the history of the Japanese American Research Project (JARP) see Yasuo Sakata's introduction in A Buried Past: An Annotated Bibliography of the Japanese American Research Project Collection, (Berkeley; University of California Press, 1974).
Organization and Arrangement
Estelle Ishigo papers are found in Boxes 77-81, 719, 769, 781, 783, 788, and 863 of the
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States(Collection 2010).
Arranged in the following series:
Biographical materials and internment camp correspondence (Box 77).
Documents, records, and other materials relating to Estelle's life in the Heart Mountain Relocation Camp and Federal Public Housing Authority resettlement trailer camps in Southern California (Box 78).
Correspondence and documents relating to the Ishigo's evacuation claims and manuscripts for Estelle Ishigo's short stories and essays (Box 79).
Miscellany and published materials (Box 80).
Artwork at the relocation camp (Boxes 81, 719, 769, 781, 783, 788, 863).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Ishigo, Estelle--Archives.; Women artists--California--Archival resources.; Japanese evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles).
Genres and Forms of Material
Manuscripts for publication.; Correspondence.; Watercolors.; Drawings.; Photographs.; Ishigo, Arthur.
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at the UCLA LIbrary Special Collections.
Days of Waiting1990.28 minutes/Color/VHS-NTSC video-tape.
Copyright owned by Mouchette Films. Produced and directed by Steven Okazaki.
Library Special Collections Backlog #146433.
Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library.
Lone Heart Mountain1972.
Estelle Ishigo.
Book with illustrations. 104pp. 26 centimeters. Call Number D 769.8 A6I7.
Container List
- Ishigo papers., 1941-1957.; 8.5 linear ft.
  - Biographical Materials and Internment Camp Correspondence., .5 linear ft.
    - Incidental papers containing biographical information on Estelle Ishigo and her husband.., ca. 1954-ca. 1957.; (6 items) (Box 77, Folder 1)
      - Ishigo family, Japan.., n.d.; Item no. 1; (1 p.; 13 x 10 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 1)
        A very brief handwritten "family tree" of Arthur Ishigo's family starting with "Grand father". Also lists cities in Japan. Japanese characters are written along the upper right hand side.
      - Estelle and Arthur Ishigo., Item no. 2; (3 p.; 21 x 13 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 1)
        Handwritten biographical notes on Estelle's and Arthur's lives post WWII.
      - Wife of Ishigo Shigeharu., Date Created: 1957(?).; Item no. 3; (2 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 1)
        Handwritten draft of what appears to be an inquiry about the Ishigo family. Estelle was trying to get information on Arthur Ishigo's younger brother. Includes some Japanese characters in the body of the text.
      - Estelle Ishigo: résumé (draft)., Date Created: 1957.; Item no. 4; (1 p.; 21 x 13 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 1)
        Handwritten resume covering the years from 1940 to the present (1957?).
      - Los Angeles City Civil Service Commission: application for examination., n.d.; Item no. 5; (4 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 1)
        Application for the position of radio telephone operator.
      - Ishigo family; and, Property of Arthur Shigeharu Ishigo., Date Created: 1959.; Item no. 6; (2 p.; 28 x 22 cm.); (Handwritten, with Japanese characters on upper left corner. (Box 77, Folder 1)
        Top half of recto includes a very brief family tree and lists the places in Japan where members of the Ishigo family lived; bottom half is a listing of Arthur Ishigo's personal possessions in 1959.
    - Letters and postcards Estelle Ishigo received from her Caucasian friends in the Pomona Assembly Center and the Heart Mountain Relocation Camp., 1942-1945.; (73 items) (Box 77, Folder 2-3)
      - Letter, 1942 May 13, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Ishigo, Pomona Assembly Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: May 13, 1942.; Item no. 1; (2 p.; 28 x 22 cm.); (Handwritten. (Box 77, Folder 2)
        A letter from the Ishigos' good friend Lew Brown, sent shortly after they had arrived at the Pomona barracks.
      - Letter, 1942 June 9, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: June 9, 1942.; Item no. 2 (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, 1942 June 20, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mr. and Mrs. Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: June 20, 1942.; Item no. 3; (2 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        A letter from their good friend Lew who is planning a trip to visit Estelle and Arthur. He asks that they arrange for him to have a pass so that he can visit.
      - Letter, 1942 July 11, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: July 11, 1942.; Item no. 4; (2 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        Handwritten letter to the Ishigos from their good friend Lew Brown. He explains that he tried to go to the gallery to check on Estelle's paintings but it was closed.
      - Letter, 1942 July 19, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: July 19, 1942.; Item no. 5; (2 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        Lew Brown writes of finally speaking with Mrs. Rodman regarding the paintings she is trying to sell for Estelle and Arthur.
      - Postcard, 1942 December 17, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mr. and Mrs. Ishigo., Date Created: December 17, 1942.; Item no. 6; (1 postcard; 8 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, 1943 January 13, Hollywood, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: January 13, 1943.; Item no. 7; (2 p.; 20 x 16 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, 1943 October 14, Hollywood, Calif. to Mrs Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: October 14, 1943.; Item no. 8; (4 p.; 21 x 13 cm.); (Handwritten) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        Estelle's friend Grayce writes asking if she needs anything and informs Estelle that she is having difficulty locating some of the music that she requested.
      - Letter, 1943 November 2, Los Angeles, Calif to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: November 2, 1943.; Item no. 9; (2 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        Grayce asks how Estelle is doing. She wonders if leg makeup would work for Arthur as she cannot locate face makeup.
        Handwritten on letterhead from County of Los Angeles Office of the Sheriff.
      - Christmas card to Arthur and Estelle Ishigo., Date Created: December 1943 (?).; Item no. 10; (1 card (4 p.): col. ill.; 30 x 24 cm. folded to 15 x 12 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        Christmas greetings from Zabelle.
      - Christmas card to Arthur and Estelle Ishigo., Date Created: December 1944 (?).; Item no. 11; (1 card (4 p.): col.; 26 x 21 cm. folded to 13 x 10 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        Christmas card from friend Lew Brown. He writes that he hopes this will be the last Christmas Estelle and Arthur spend in exile.
      - Christmas card to Arthur and Estelle Ishigo., Date Created: December 1943.; Item no. 12; (1 sheet (4 p.); col.; 26 x 24 cm. folded to 13 x 12 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        Christmas card sent to the Ishigos at Heart Mountain.
      - Letter, 1944 December 3, to Estelle Ishigo., Date Created: December 3, 1944.; Item no. 13; (1 p.; 31 x 20 cm. folded to 20 x 15.5 cm.); (Handwritten); (1 p. folded to 3 sections) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        A holiday letter from friend Grayce. Includes a one page letter from Grayce's mother, Mrs. Haroutunian. They both express the hope that the Arthur and Estelle will be back home come next Christmas.
      - Letter, to Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Ishigo., Item no. 14; (1 p.; 27 x 17 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, 1945 August 5, Hollywood, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: August 5, 1945.; Item no. 15; (1 sheet (3 p.); 17 x 26 cm. folded to 17 x 13 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Christmas card to Arthur and Estelle Ishigo., Item no. 16; (1 card: col. ill.; 11.5 x 30 cm. folded to 11.5 x 15 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, 1942 May 16 to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: May 16, 1942.; Item no. 17; (1 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, 1942 May 19, to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Assembly Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: May 19, 1942.; Item no. 18; (1 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Assembly Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: June 15, 1942.; Item no. 19 (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Assembly Center, Pomona, Calif., July 4, 1942.; Item no. 20 (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., August 6, 1942.; Item no. 21 (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: October 25, 1942.; Item no. 22; (1 p.; 25 x 20 cm. folded to 20 x 13 cm.); (1 page folded to 3 sections) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: January 17, 1943.; Item no. 23; (1 p.; 25 x 20 cm. folded to 20 x 13 cm.); (1 page folded to 3 sections) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, Pasadena, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: July 17, 1944.; Item no. 24; (4 p.; 17 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, Pasadena, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: August 15, 1944.; Item no. 25; (2 p.; 28 x 21.5 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, Denver, Colo. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: November 25, 1943.; Item no. 26; (1 p.; 18 x 28 cm. folded to 18 x 14 cm.; 1 card, col. ill.; 21 x 11 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
        A letter from a friend of Estelle Ishigo's thanking her for a painting she received. The correspondent also notes that the editor of the "Pacific Citizen" may contact Estelle for permission to reprint one of her paintings.
      - Letter, Camp Grant, Ill. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo., Date Created: April 20, 1942.; Item no. 27; (1 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Evacuees: dedicated to Estelle Ishigo and her symbolic painting of Heart Mountain., Date Created: October, 17, 1943.; Item no. 28; (1 p.; 27 x 21 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 2)
      - Letter, North Hollywood, Calif. to Estelle and Arthur Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, CA., Date Created: June 7, 1942.; Item no. 1; (2 p.; 17 x 13 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        A handwritten letter from friend Lynn Hackett. On verso of letter is a list, presumably written by Estelle Ishigo, of food staples that Lynn and Rose Hackett can bring to Estelle and Arthur.
      - Letter, Hollywood, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: June 29, 1942.; Item no. 2; (1 p.; 27 x 19 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Letter informing Estelle that L.H. has written to Mr. Baron on Estelle's behalf but to no avail.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: February 2, 1942.; Item no. 4; (6 p.; 26 x 17 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Cody, Wyoming., Date Created: November 9, 1942.; Item no. 3; (2 p.; 23 x 16 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Signed by "the Ahlers", proprietors of Superior Transfer & Storage Co.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle and Arthur Ishigo, Heart Mountain, Wyoming., Date Created: June 17, 1943.; Item no. 5; (1 p.; 23 x 16 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
      - Announcing the marriage of Dorothy Lorraine Ahlers to Mr. Richard Murray Salisbury., Date Created: June 7, 1942.; Item no. 6; (2 p.; 17 x 13 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
      - Letter, Santa Cruz, Calif. to Mrs. Ishigo, Los Angeles, Calif., Date Created: May 1, 1941.; Item no. 7; (1 p.; 26 x 21 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        A handwritten letter from the Ishigos' landlord authorizing Estelle to hire a plumber to repair the plumbing but to please try and keep the cost down.
      - Letter, Santa Cruz, Calif. to Mr. & Mrs. Ishigo, Los Angeles, Calif., Date Created: May 3, 1942.; Item no. 8; (3 p.; 23 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Letter (from landlords) requesting that Estelle Ishigo send a list of items left in their Los Angeles home after relocating.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Mrs. Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Assembly Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: May 12, 1942.; Item no. 9; (1 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Letter from a friend of Estelle Ishigo's writing about cleaning out the Ishigos' Los Angeles residence after they were relocated.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: August 6, 1942.; Item no. 10; (6 p.; 28 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        These are two letters sent together. The first is dated "Aug 6" and the second simply "Thursday". Page "3" recto/verso is half a sheet with a sketch on recto.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: August 6, 1942.; Item no. 11; (1 folded leaf (2 p.); 19 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Brief letter from the Ishigos' friend Ruth asking Estelle to please arrange for a visitation pass so that Ruth and Ty can visit them. Also, Ruth asks what they can bring them. On upper left corner of "outside spread" of image is written: "Cotton tobacco", presumably by Estelle.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Assembly Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: May 16, 1942.; Item no. 12; (1 folded leaf (4 p.); 22 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Letter from friend and actress Lois Hunt.
      - Postcard, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: May 21, 1942.; Item no. 13; (1 postcard; 7.5 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        A brief note from friend Lois.
      - Postcard, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Assembly Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: May 18, 1942.; Item no. 14; (1 postcard; 8 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Brief note letting Estelle know that Bill has taken care of Arthur's toolbox.
      - Postcard, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: May 23, 1942.; Item no. 15; (1 postcard; 8 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Brief note from Lois letting Estelle and Art know that she is sending them raisins and cigarette papers.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, California., Date Created: June 2, 1942.; Item no. 16; (2 p.; 24 x 22 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Letter from friend Lois telling Estelle that she has sent her soya leaves and wonders what other supplies they might need. Lois also talks about her theater work.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, California., Date Created: June 11, 1942.; Item no. 17; (4 p.; 17 x 13 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Lois congratulates Estelle and the others who worked on the "Pomona Center News."
      - Postcard, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: June 15, 1942.; Item no. 18; (1 postcard; 7 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Lois asks Estelle if she can arrange visitors' passes for Bill and herself. Asks if there is anything they can bring. Written along the bottom in pencil: "Bot. witch hazel."
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: June 26, 1942.; Item no. 19; (3 p.; 17 x 13 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: July 1, 1942.; Item no. 20; (1 folded sheet (4 p., last page blank); 23 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: July 9, 1942.; Item no. 21; (6 p.; 16 x 13 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Lois asks Estelle about the violin lessons she (Estelle) is giving and updates her on the latest news from home.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: July 23, 1942.; Item no. 22; (1 folded sheet (4 p.); 22 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
      - Postcard, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: July 19, 1942.; Item no. 23; (1 postcard; 8.5 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
      - Letter, Hollywood, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: August 5, 1942.; Item no. 24; (1 folded sheet (4 p.); 22 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Lois lets Estelle know that she is doing all she can to get Estelle the music she requested.
      - Letter, Tule Lake, Calif. to Lois Hunt, Los Angeles, Calif., n.d.; Item no. 25; (3 p.; 23 x 15 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)
        Letter signed by "Ruth". She thanks Lois for sending her a copy of the Pomona Camp newspaper which is much better than the one at Tule Lake. Tells Lois there are at least 16,000 people at Tule Lake.
      - Letter, Los Angeles, Calif. to Estelle Ishigo, Pomona Reception Center, Pomona, Calif., Date Created: August 9, 1942.; Item no. 26; (1 folded sheet (4 p., last p. blank); 22 x 14 cm.) (Box 77, Folder 3)